Right. Now we're in...
We're in public.
We're in public. Okay, we're in public on this one. Right, cool. Right, great.
Thank you very much for the response that you've given us.
Do you want to say anything, or do you want us to go straight to questions?
And I think what we'll do is we've got 20 minutes between you,
or 10 each in theory, so we'll just do this
as a team effort, shall we?
Yep. I think that's easier, yes.
Yeah, cool. Right. If there's anything you wanted to-
Yeah, I've got a few opening remarks
...kick us off. Right, cool
So, good morning chair and members of the committee.
My name is Robyn Elston, I'm the National Manager of Local Government at NZTA
Waka Kotahi, and we appreciate the opportunity to appear
before the committee regarding the petition of Free Fares New Zealand, stop the
proposed public transport fare hikes.
I'd like to start by directly addressing the central concern
raised in the petition. NZTA recognizes that fare increases
can affect affordability and can be challenging for some public transport
users, particularly during a period of ongoing cost of living pressures.
We also recognize the important role public transport plays in supporting access to
work, education, healthcare, and community participation,
as well as its contribution to reducing congestion and supporting environmental
outcomes.
However, public transport services must also be financially
sustainable. Over recent years, the proportion of public transport
operating costs funded through private revenue has fallen significantly.
National private share was approximately 33% in
2018/2019, and had declined to
10% by 2022/23. As
private share declined, a greater proportion of operating costs was funded by
taxpayers and ratepayers. In response to GPS and Land
Transport 24 setting the expectation that public transport authorities
work towards increasing private share over time, and NZTA's
role is to implement that direction.
It is important to be clear about what NZTA does and does not do.
NZTA does not set public transport fares, determine concession
policies, or decide local service levels.
Except for SuperGold and Community Connect, which are set by the government, the
remaining transport fares concession policy decisions remain the
responsibility of public transport authorities and their elected
representatives. NZTA has not directed councils to
implement specific fare increases.
Our role has been to work alongside public transport authorities to establish
appropriate targets and support them in identifying how those targets can
be achieved.
When developing those targets, NZTA engaged extensively
with public transport authorities across the country.
Following that engagement, the final targets were approved by the NZTA board,
and they were lower than those that were originally proposed and were tailored to
regional circumstances.
NZTA also encouraged authorities to consider approaches that avoided
adverse outcomes, such as significant patronage
decline.
Ultimately, we do not see this as a choice between affordable public transport and
sustainable public transport.
The challenge is finding the right balance between affordability, patronage growth,
environmental objectives, and long-term funding sustainability.
And NZTA's role is to support that balance while implementing the expectations set
by government through GPS '24. Thank you.
Thank you, Robyn.
We've questions.
We're good for questions?
Yes.
Okay, right. Cool. Who's going to kick us off? Julianne?
Thanks so much, Robyn. I'm just wondering if you can confirm that
the rationale that you just gave for
having a policy to get a greater share of funding from private share in a very
short term is something that was set by the government.
It's a policy decision set by the government of the day.
It's not a rationale
that maybe
would exist independently.
Like if you went out to other places, other cities, other countries,
this isn't an approach that is
necessarily deemed the best approach from a public policy
point of view.
We were implementing the GPS.
Yeah. And that was a choice, a political choice. Thanks.
I'm going to imagine that there is no particular right answer to the
proportion of
private share in any public transport system.
It is, as Julianne has said, a policy decision
to what proportion, but there's no right or wrong answer in this, is there?
The 33% that we started off with in 2018,
what was the trend before that? Was it pretty much it had been
reasonably stable to that point?
Sorry, Chair, I don't know the answer to that. Do you know the answer to that?
Well, it's one thing to say, look, it had peaked.
Had it gone up to 33% from some lower number was
another thing.
No, I think it had been-
So it actually had been traditionally around that.
So-
I understand it's been relatively stable.
Sorry?
It's been stable around there, but I can get you that information.
It'd be useful to know what the long-term trajectory had been.
And then the other thing is just in terms of the reduction,
so it dropped down to a low of about 11 you said.
To what degree that was driven by reductions in fares,
and obviously there was some very temporary reductions in fares through COVID, et
cetera, which were clearly one-offs.
Yeah.
And then to what extent it was driven by increases in the cost
of the services. We've got quite a number of things, the change to the PTOM
model, increase in
remuneration. I'm not sure if the
move to electric buses will do it because that's long-term.
You said it was actually cost beneficial, but it'll be interesting to know what
drove that drop because that's a huge drop from
33% to 11
Yeah.
Chair, it's a mix. The cost of providing public
transport has gone up. It's around about 4%, I think, per year
in terms of costs going up, and fares have not increased.
PTAs have not
significantly increased fares over that period.
So they're absorbing more costs.
And changes to
half-price fares and
those and concessions have all played their role because it's
a balance between-
Okay. About 4%, though, that's a useful thing.
And look, my final area of question there before I go.
I think, Tangy, you've got a question, and then I got Dan.
My other area of question, just the concessions.
You just said the only one left is Community Services card. Oh, and SuperGold.
Children are also half price up to age 15 or
while they're still at school too.
There's definitely a concession for children.
Yep.
Can be slightly different in different regions-
Yeah
... in terms of how they're setting it.
Mm.
There's also some tertiary students.
Yeah.
Uh-
But that's a choice of the PTA or the-
Correct
... the council that's in charge them. Yeah.
Correct.
Cool. Right. Thank you. Tangy.
Thank you, Mr. Chair. Thank you. My question is about the extent of engagement
with local authorities around the
setting of the targets and the increase in share.
What was the sort of nature of concerns that were expressed by
authorities around the ability to achieve that?
You talked about the requirement to engage and that the board ultimately
formed a view, but what was the nature of
that engagement and concern?
Conversations, as I understand it, I wasn't there.
Sure.
As I understand it, we worked with each PTA to understand their
unique circumstances in their community, so about
where they were at in terms of
their strategy, what their elected members were
asking for, what the
regional council
focus in that one, and also
trying to balance the effect of...
So
increase in private share does not automatically mean an increase
in public, in fares. There are other ways to
achieve
an increase in private share, such as reducing operating
costs,
seeking third-party revenue. So it was that opportunity
that each of the PTAs would have different ways of seeking
those to balance that. So.
And I
appreciate that there will be different bits of
feedback across the country, but were there any
common sort of themes or threads about an inability or
difficulty from the sector to be able to achieve what
was being asked?
I believe so. Again, I wasn't there.
But you would've seen that
there was an original
proposal around the extent that private share should
increase, and that was changed as a result of the
conversations with the PTA. So that would suggest that there was some
challenges that
NZTA took on board and the NZTA board took on board.
Dan.
Thanks, Mr. Chair. Thank you.
That 33% to 11% is quite a dramatic drop.
I'm just wondering if
there's any indication on the cost to NZTA
and taxpayers for all that dramatic
change
or drop in private.
The increase, so
public transport services is funded through the
NLTF.
Yeah.
And
for the '24, '27, there was
3.7 billion set aside for public transport services.
And that was slightly less than the '20,
'21
GPS or period. So,
not dramatically increased, but the subsidy, what
it means is that the PTAs then need to work out they're getting this amount of
money from NLTF, they've got rate payers, and they've got
third-party revenue. So they would need to think about how they
manage
the delivery of public transport services with that amount of money and
costs going up.
So fair to say that if NZTA's NTF funding
has an increase, it means local authorities would be
increasing their share of-
Potentially or- Yeah. Potentially.
Yes.
The other source would be the Crown for some of those fare
concessions that came in around that time were Crown funded.
So there might be other
sources that are the taxpayer.
Backups. Yeah. Okay.
Julian.
Oh, yeah. As kind of a sub on that. If I recall correctly,
was there ever some climate
response fund funding for public transport fares?
No, for buses.
Oh.
No. Getting-
Oh, for the decarbonization, and that was coming from ETS revenue.
Oh, so that was for the electrification of buses, was it?
Yeah.
Yeah. Okay. Yep.
But
if I recall correctly,
Otago Regional Council
did a big change to services and fares in Queenstown,
where the airport service was, like, $13 or
whatever, and nobody was taking it.
And they
increased the frequency and dropped the fare to $2,
and their overall revenue went up.
So, I guess it's possible to have a
situation where you're dropping fares and increasing services,
and in the short term, it looks like that'll be an increase in cost.
But in the long run, it actually improves your revenue situation, and I
think I'm just wondering is that able to be
taken into account? Because we've heard a lot from
public transport authorities that they are having to put up fares
more than they would like because of the government policies.
On private share
We do know that patronage
does go up, and so you can get an increase in
revenue just due to patronage. But
it's a
balance.
I think the same was true in Wellington, where the geniuses
decided they would take the airport flyer,
its previous guise, off snapper. Didn't tell anybody when it was going to
be there, reduced the frequency,
increased the fares.
Of course, it fell apart, and then after COVID came back and it worked much better.
So, yeah.
Can I just ask one other question, which is just the overall trajectory.
I think that's where Dan was going, but I'm not quite sure.
The overall trajectory of the support for public transport from
the NLTF, going to give us that
33% and what that looked like in terms of the share that was coming
from private versus Crown over
time. It would be quite good also to understand what the trajectory has been of the
Crown subsidy in one way or the other for public transport-
We can provide the committee with that information
Okay. And the other part of that is just in terms of those capital projects,
Julianne's mentioned the funding that
was given through an ETS type fund for
electrification of buses.
How do we put in... If you do, for example, let's say you do the Eastern Busway,
for example, or you do a major transport interchange, whatever it might be.
Does that get factored into that,
the money which goes into public trans-- It doesn't? Okay.
It's private. It's public transport infrastructure activity
class. So-
So do we charge that back to the cost of the provision
of the service? In other words,
often you might say, well, look, it's capital cost, but what we'll do
is we'll charge the depreciation of interest back to the-
No
So we don't.
No.
It would be good to understand that as well.
Yeah.
Just what investments we've made, because otherwise that's a hidden subsidy there.
Just like people would argue on the other side of it, there's a hidden subsidy when
you build a new motorway, whatever it might be. Yeah. Okay, that'd be helpful.
Carlos.
Thank you.
On your witness submission, you actually mentioned certain areas the bus fare
actually haven't increased. Some even haven't increased for the last
20 years. So can I ask how bus fare
increase in New Zealand overall keep pace with the inflation and the
rising operational cost of providing public bus service?
How does it?
Sorry, I didn't hear your question that well.
Have the bus fare increase in New Zealand keep
pace with inflation and the rising
operational cost of providing public bus service?
If the fees haven't increased and costs have gone up, then no, it
hasn't. But that's a choice of each public transport
authority and the way they balance their
rate payer
support, their
public transport's contribution from NLTF and private
share. And some PTAs
are
being challenged in terms of delivering public transport services.
So what you say is the bus fare doesn't really
keep up with the inflation.
Am I correct? And the operational cost increase.
I think it depends on each public transport authority.
I don't know the specific information to answer that
question accurately.
Mm-hmm.
But if you haven't increased fees over a certain period,
you would be looking at patronage and costs as a way of
managing
to ensure that you had a sustainable public transport service.
Sure.
Cool. Are there any other questions?
Okay, so just in terms of this, we
will have to write a report in due course.
But obviously, there's some information we've asked you to bring back.
So if we can do that, what sort of timeframe to be able to bring that back?
It shouldn't be hard.
Sorry?
It shouldn't be hard. We can do it in a week, two
weeks.
Yeah.
Okay. Well, let's aim for next week, and then we can get a report done.
But very much appreciated. Look, we really appreciate-
Thank you
... your input so far. Oh, sorry, Julianne, you've got one more.
Sorry, I was just wondering
if it'd be possible for you to give us some
information about relative affordability of public
transport
in Auckland compared to other cities in Australia or other cities you have
data for.
We can.
That would be great.
Can you also give us some of the operational costs in Auckland and Wellington,
those major cities as well? How much is it cost then
compared to the inflation as well? I think that would be great.
Thank you.
Have you kept note of the things we've asked you?
I'm trying to.
Because otherwise we will have to collectively make sure we have.
Sorry, you've got a list of the things we've asked you there?
Yeah.
I think so, between us. Yep.
Sorry?
I think we do between us.
Okay, cool. That's brilliant.
Thank you.
Thanks very much.
Thank you very much. Really appreciate it, and we'll look forward to seeing you
again next week.
Thank you.
Morning.
Thank you for being here.
No, this one is in-
Morning.
Okay. Right. So what we're going to do is
we've had correspondence. Thank you for responding to the
summons.
And I think what I'm going to do is go straight, if you're okay with that, straight
to questions.
Sure.
Okay. Thanks.
Sure. Thank you. And thank you both for coming in.
And thank you for the
correspondence that you've given to the committee.
You'll recall back in early December, I asked a number of questions
that related to the former employment of Mr.
Dewatna.
Mm-hmm.
Looking at the transcript, there were three specific occasions that you
as chief executive indicated that you would come back to the
committee with that. Do you accept that that commitment was made to the committee?
Yes, absolutely.
Yes, okay. When was the decision made to ultimately not release that information to
the committee?
I think in that committee meeting,
Kane had said that we'd take advice and then come back to you.
And the
facts that we did not are not in dispute, and we've extended an
apology for that on the 6th of May in writing.
The media also had significant interest in that that day and the following day, and
we did put out
some public commentary that we were unable to
make any comments regarding that.
We then followed up with Mr. Dewatna in person.
We did receive his
permission to waive his privacy on it, and we did go out
publicly to state
the nature of his settlement payment.
And if I can add to that, I don't think there was a decision not to provide the
committee with information. The sequence of events was,
we'd committed to take some further advice on what information we could
share with the committee, which we did.
Between the committee hearing
and the written request for
further information from the committee, which I think was later in December just
before Christmas,
we had received a number of OIA requests from media outlets,
particularly in relation to the details around
the arrangements with Mr. Dewatna, which we had
provided. So we had assumed wrongly, with the benefit of hindsight,
that when the committee had followed up with subsequent requests for
information, which didn't include information about Mr.
Dewatna's arrangements,
that because it had been in the public domain, there wasn't any need to provide any
further information.
That's why I think in the letter that we'd responded, we said actually we've made
some changes to our process, which is if we've made the commitment to get back to
the committee, particularly in a case like this, what ought to have happened is
that we should have provided that information to the committee as we were
responding to official information requests.
I'm pleased to hear that. I guess we have a circumstance here where in the
committee's own letter to you, it has formed the view that the
behavior and conduct of the CAA is highly disrespectful to
parliamentary proceedings. And so I guess we're interested, well, I'm
interested in what specifically has been put in place with the
authority to ensure that if a parliamentary select committee
undertaking an annual review of your organization has asked you specific
questions, and then to read about those answers in the media,
that is highly disrespectful.
So what specifically has been put in place to ensure that that will not happen
again?
So the process we have in place now,
so obviously we'll have an annual review hearing coming up in a few months,
is that if there are questions that come out of the committee where we've made a
commitment to come back, we will progress those
commitments rather than wait for the committee to provide us follow-up questions.
As I said, if I was to rerun what
ought to have happened in this case, if we were to put that new process in place,
we would provide the information that ultimately leaked to the
public to this committee at the time or prior to that
information going out in the public domain.
Mr. Derrick, as chair,
when were you made aware that the commitment to this committee had not been
fulfilled?
When I received a letter.
From the committee?
That's right. On the 30th of April.
So you were here at the
start of December when this exchange took place,
and then it's not until the end of April that you were made
aware of the sort of breakdown in
process?
Yes, that's correct.
Okay.
Mr. Patino, that's quite a significant period of time given that the
request from the committee had
sort of come even in later
December.
Mr. Derrick, do you have concerns about
that fact? Basically, this committee was sitting,
waiting for in excess of four months for a
response that had been widely circulated amongst the media.
Look, I think
it's been taken very seriously.
Myself and the board have made sure
that through the governance teams and the communications team, this can't happen
again. So it has been taken very seriously and the remedials have been put in
place.
I have some sympathy, and this is not an excuse, but I have some sympathy
with the fact that
the following days after the committee, we were inundated with media inquiries.
So our team were pretty frenetically dealing with
OIAs and media,
and this was missed, and that's unacceptable.
It didn't help with the follow-up letter from the committee, didn't include that
question and could have. And our team had assumed
incorrectly that the matter had been satisfied.
But when you go through the facts, they're not in dispute and
I'm satisfied that the team have taken it seriously enough that
the processes in place after a meeting from this committee are quite different.
In terms of the specific information that was requested,
can we just now move to that? So the three
questions that I asked was, what was the value of the remuneration as part
of the notice period? Do you accept you've provided that information to the
committee
now?
I now accept that, but as I understand, the information that's been provided to the
committee was that
Mr. Dewatna had been paid four months in lieu of notice.
We'd provided the salary band
for Mr. Dewatna's remuneration. So it
doesn't provide a specific number,
but at least provides an indication to the committee of what the
arrangements were.
You still maintain that it's not appropriate to provide that specific number, given
that the question I asked in the hearing was that figures had been
disclosed by Mr. Foster
around the Public Service Commission, by PharmG and by the Ministry of
Health, and that there potentially is an inconsistency in
disclosure requirements on the part of the CAA?
What we're trying to balance here is firstly the
need to ensure that
the general public and the committee has information on an issue of
public interest,
while at the same time ensuring that we meet our responsibilities
as an employer, which of course continues even after, in this case, Mr.
Dewatna's resignation. And so,
the reason why we needed to go back and have a look at this
further was to ensure that if we were providing further information related
specifically to Mr. Dewatna's employment situation and personal information
related to him, that we were able to get that balance right and not necessarily
breach our obligations as an employer.
That's why when we provided information to the committee, we were able to provide
with Mr. Dewatna's consent,
the notice period and the salary range within which he was
employed.
Did Mr. Dewatna, in providing consent, waive his
right to privacy? Or did he
give permission for the band as opposed to the specific number?
He had consented to the information that we
provided to the public and the committee.
So it wasn't a blanket waiver of his privacy.
It was specific to the information that had been
released.
Did you engage with him about releasing the
specific amount of remuneration to this committee?
We had provided Mr. Dewatna with
the questions that we had been asked, both from the committee and also
within the media, which of course was specifics.
So he was provided with
questions that we needed to respond to.
And it was through conversations with Mr.
Dewatna that he was happy to consent to the information that was provided.
So just to be clear, the specific question I asked you from the transcript was
what's the value of that remuneration as part of the notice period.
Did you put that to Mr. Dewatna
as the specific question?
I'll need to go back and double-check exactly what was put to Mr.
Dewatna, but what I do know is that he was provided with the specific questions
that we were asked,
both from the committee and also from general
OIA requests that we had received as well, which of course I know was
specifically related to what was the actual sum or quantum.
Okay. Well, we'll look forward to that coming back to the committee.
Those are all the questions I have, Mr. Chair.
Thanks, Tangy.
Yeah.
Just one from me, and that's just in terms of the
key issue which we had here. There was a lot of extended questioning during
the hearing from Tangy Te Keri on this
matter.
But the key question for me is, and the reason you're here is because of the
failure to actually come back with the information that, in fact, I think you said
weren't going to come back with the information, which obviously was, you've heard
from a parliamentary respect for parliament and parliamentary process
we're very unhappy with.
To what degree are you able to share that lesson
with other
institutions through the public sector?
Because we don't want to see it from other organizations either.
I don't know what level of interface you have with other chief executives, chairs
through the system so that we actually, everybody's got the message.
I think this public meeting is a good place to start.
But both Ken and I move in a lot of circles, and we'll
certainly be passing on this experience and
the learning from it.
That would be very helpful.
Yeah. A lot more so.
We don't really want to see other organizations-
Quite right
... make the same errors and
have to go through the same process.
It was, just to close, it was not deliberate.
It was an oversight, and for that, we have extended our apology.
I think we accept that, but it's a lesson if we can learn and quite do things-
Yes
... optimally, that is a good thing. Any other questions, colleagues?
I think he's covered it, so.
Okay. Well, look, on that basis, thank you very much.
Thank you.
Thank you for the acknowledgement of the
error.
Unintended as it was, but
we can all learn from it. That's a good thing.
Great.
Thank you.
Thanks, Mark.
Thank you very much.
Thank you.